（イタチ）このまま少し　ループにかけて→
It makes it easier to cast
my real Visual Genjutsu on him
本来の視覚による幻術に
かけやすくする。
by keeping him trapped in
a small loop like this.
（サスケ）なら…。
So Kabuto's trapped in
your loop now?
カブトは　そのループってのに
ハマったってことか？
それが　イザナミ…。
And that's the Izanami?
いつ　仕掛けた？
When did you cast it?
（イタチ）カブトが最初に　俺を
その刀で突き刺したときだ。
The first time Kabuto stabbed me
with that blade.
あのときか…。
Back then, huh?
しかし　どうやって？
But how?
視覚に訴えることなく→
You mentioned a Visual Jutsu
that is possible without sight.
ハメる瞳術があると
言っていたが…。
視覚じゃない瞳術とは
どういうことだ？
How can Visual Jutsu work
without eyesight?
イザナミは　自分と相手…。
Izanami is a Visual Jutsu that
works with the physical senses
２人の体の感覚によって
ハメる瞳術だ。
of both yourself and your opponents.
２人の体の感覚？
The physical senses of two people?
行動の中の任意の一瞬…。
As you are battling your opponent,
you take a record, like a photograph,
その一瞬の
己と相手の体の感覚を→
of the physical senses that
both you and your opponent
一度　瞳術で
写真のように記憶する。
are feeling during that instant,
with your Visual Jutsu.
仮に　それをＡとする。
We'll call that A.
更に　時の流れの中で→
As time progresses,
より印象的な場面をＢ　Ｃと→
you find "B" is a more
important moment,
then you record "C" and
so on with Sharingan.
次々に写輪眼で記憶する。
一定の瞬間を記憶したら→
Then you recreate
those exact physical senses.
前に記憶したＡと
同じ体の感覚を→
So you're using your powers to
create an exact copy of A.
わざと　もう一度再現させた
Ａ´を作る。
We'll call this A'.
イザナミは　そのＡと　Ａ´を重ね→
By overlaying
and connecting A to A',
FLOW OF TIME
更には　Ｂ´
Ｃ´を再現することにより→
the Izanami also links
a path for B' and C'
一定の時間の中を　さまよわせる。
to create fluctuations within
a fixed time.
つまり　無限ループを作る能力だ。
In other words, it's the power
to create an infinite loop.
もちろん
失明することと引き換えにする。
Naturally, all in exchange for
one's own sight of course,
イザナギと同じにな。
exactly like Izanagi.
カブトの意識は
その幻のイタチと俺を相手に→
So Kabuto's consciousness
is trapped inside
fighting a phantom you and
a phantom me for all eternity.
ずっと無限に続くループの中で
閉じ込められるってわけか…。
いや…　この術には→
No.
There is an escape route built
into the jutsu.
そのループから抜け出る道が
用意されている。
そもそも　イザナミは→
The Izanami was developed
to admonish
イザナギの術者を戒め
救うために作られた術だからな。
and save an Izanagi user.
どういうことだ？
What does that mean?
イザナギは　お前も少し
知っているようだが…。
You know a little about
the Izanagi already.
あれは　運命を変える→
It's called the perfect
Uchiha Visual Jutsu
うちはの完璧な瞳術だと
いわれていたそうだ。
designed to change destiny.
己の結果に
うまくいかないことがあれば→
If something does not go
the way you want it to,
その結果をかき消し
もとに戻れる。
you can just erase that outcome
and start all over.
いわば　都合のいい結果だけを
選び取っていける仕組みだ。
Ultimately, you can pick
and choose
the most desirable end result.
これから語るのは
イザナギと対をなす→
What I'm about to tell you now
is the story
イザナミが誕生した
うちはの歴史の一部だ。
of the Uchiha's Izanami,
and how it came to be.
お前にも
知っておいてもらいたい。
I want you to know this too.
うちはの…。
The Uchiha's Izanami...
the story of its creation?
イザナミ誕生の歴史…。
for some reason the moon is one size larger tonight
konya no tsuki wa nazeka hitomawari ookikute
it's shining brighter than it usually does
itsumo yori akaruku terasu
I trudge along the road home with my shoulders hunched
senaka wo marumete tobotobo kaeru michi
at any time I will always have a friend
donna toki mo mikata wa iru
without saying a word, it's all right to cry
nani mo iwazu naketara ii ne
once my tears dry, it will all be over
namida ga karetara owari
I need to become stronger...
motto boku ga tsuyoku naranakya
sorrow is the first step towards independence
kanashimi wa jiritsu he no ippo
how many times do I have to get hurt to forget the pain?
nando kizutsukeba itami wo wasureru
when I bleed red, I'm reminded of life
akai chi wo nagaseba inochi wo omoidasu sa
I collapse on the road with my arms and legs spread out
michi ni taore dainoji ni
I look up at the sky and think
sora wo miagete omou
true loneliness is someone without a past
shin no kodoku to wa kako no nai mono
someone who only knows the present
ima shika shiranu mono
Izanagi and Izanami
Long ago, there was
a great battle
過去の大きな戦いにおいて→
that the Uchiha Clan could not
afford to lose.
うちは一族が
決して失敗できぬとき→
The Izanagi tuned out
to be invaluable.
イザナギが
大きく貢献する術となった。
Go!
((ライ：いけっ！
（みんな）うわ～！
Damn it! They had set a trap!
おのれ！　罠を仕掛けていたか！
What?!
なにっ！？
Die!
殲滅せよ！
As long as we have the Izanagi,
we can't lose!
うちはに　イザナギあるかぎり→
(我らに敗北は　ありえぬのだ！
ハッハッハ！))
が　しかし
結果を己の思うがままに→
However...
There's a bigger risk than
just blindness
変えられる術には
失明以上の大きなリスクがあった。
to a jutsu that allows the casters
to choose their own ending.
Most who used this overly
powerful Visual Jutsu
その強力すぎる瞳力は
術者をおごらせ→
could not handle it and
abused their power.
個を暴走させる
要因となってしまったらしい。
It was fine,
それでも　イザナギを使う者が
１人なら問題ない。
as long as there was
only one user of the Izanagi.
However, when two or more used it,
だが　それが２人以上となると→
there was a scramble
within the Uchiha Clan
うちは一族内で　都合のいい結果の
奪い合いが始まった。
to see who could get the best result.
You are not the only one
who can use Izanagi!
((バル：イザナギが使えるのは
お前だけではない！
I don't like you bossing us around!
お前が　リーダー面をするのは
気にくわぬ！
だが　手柄を立てたのは事実。
But I'm the one who
accomplished it!
In the shinobi world,
results count for everything!
忍の世界は　結果がすべてよ！
Well then...
I shall rewrite that result...
ほほぅ　ならば　その結果を→
我が手柄として
書き換えてやろうか。
俺の　イザナギでな！
with my Izanagi!
口ほどにもない！
You're only talk.
俺が　うちはを…。
I shall rule the Uchiha...
no, the entire shinobi world...
いや　忍世界を
仕切ってみせるわ。
with my Izanagi!
俺の　イザナギでな！
I'll take over your wish...
その野望　俺が引き継ぐ。
with my Izanagi!
この　俺のイザナギでな！
ハハハハハハ！
（ナカ）ハハハハハハ！
(ハハハハハハ！))
このような
一族内での　イザナギによる→
What was created
in order to stop this inter-clan
rivalry over the Izanagi...
都合のいい結果の奪い合い。
それを止めるために
作られたのが→
is the Izanami.
イザナミだ。
Normal vision-based genjutsu
is powerless
視覚相手に　視覚では
幻術に　ハメられないからな。
against Visual Prowess...
((ナカ：お前も
俺に刃向かうというのなら→
If you intend to oppose me too,
I have no choice.
しかたがない。
There has to be a way to
settle this without fighting.
（ナオリ）争い以外にも
解決策はあるはずよ。
ハッ！　俺の手は
すでに血で染まっている。
My hands are already stained
with blood.
立ち止まることなど
許されるはずもない！
As if I'm going to stop!
You don't know yourself!
（ナオリ）あなたは
自分をわかってない！
You don't know your own true strength!
自分自身の本当の力を
わかってないのよ。
ええい　黙れ！
Oh, shut up!
It's not too late to
turn back right now!
今なら引き返せる。
その意志があるのならば
私の手を。
If you have the will,
take my hand!
フン！　騙されるか！
I won't be fooled!
If you still refuse to listen,
I'm prepared as well.
どうしても
言うことが聞けないのなら→
私にも覚悟がある。
Sneaking up behind me, nice work!
この俺の背後をとるとは　やるな。
But as long as I have Izanagi,
you cannot beat me!
だが　イザナギがあるかぎり
俺を倒すことはできん。
It's over for you!
次で終わらせる！
ハァ…　ハァ…　ハァ…。
I don't believe this!
バカな！
My right eye...
俺の右目は　イザナギとともに
視力を失ったはず！
I should have gone blind
with the Izanagi!
The Izanagi that you depend on so much
will not protect you.
（ナオリ）あなたの頼りとするイザナギは
あなたを守ってはくれない。
Shut up!
黙れ！
(くっ…　まだ　まだだ！))
N-Not... Not yet!
In the first place,
（イタチ）そもそも　現実とは
運命という名の偶然の産物だ。
reality is a product of chance
that we call fate.
We can't predict it.
我々には　予想がつかない。
But Izanagi can twist around
an inconvenient reality
だが　イザナギは
都合の悪い現実をねじ曲げ→
and lead it to a new fate.
新たな運命を導く。
本来の現実を
術者の都合だけで→
At a whim,
REALITY
the user can change
the original reality into a new one.
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
新たな
現実へと変えてしまう。
the user can change
the original reality into a new one.
NEW REALITY
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
To the enemy,
a fallen opponent will revive,
敵からすれば
倒したはずの相手が→
To the enemy,
a fallen opponent will revive,
ANOTHER REALITY
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
復活するのだから
たまったものではない。
so it's an intolerable jutsu.
The Izanami is set up to take someone
who is using the Izanagi
IZANAMI ACTIVATED
そこで　イザナミは→
イザナギで　己の結果を
都合のいいように→
to change the outcome
to benefit oneself,
変えようとすると
一生　同じところを→
and cause them to endlessly
circle around in a loop.
グルグルと　ループさせる。
I believed that Izanagi was
the ultimate Visual Jutsu.
イザナギが
究極の瞳術だと思っていたが…。
But that means the Izanami is
a far superior Visual Jutsu.
イザナミは　その上をゆく
瞳術ということか。
Izanami forms a loop
イザナギの現実を
ねじ曲げる体感が→
around the physical sensation
of Izanagi twisting reality.
イザナミのループを
呼ぶことになるとはな…。
The Izanami is a jutsu meant
for stopping the Izanagi.
だが　イザナミは
イザナギを止めるための術。
There's an escape route built
into the loop.
ちゃんと　そのループから
抜け出る道も作られていた。
Originally, it was a jutsu
to save Uchiha comrades
これは　本来
うちはの仲間を→
おごりと怠慢から
救うための術だった。
from arrogance and negligence.
It's to stop you from taking
the easy way out with jutsu.
術で簡単に
結果から逃げる者…。
それを止めるための術。
((ハァ　ハァ…。
Why?!
なぜだ！
There's no destiny that
Izanagi cannot change!
イザナギで変えられない運命など
ないはずなのに！
Accept the things you've done,
自分のしてきたこと→
and take hold of the future
that awaits you!
そして　その先に待つ
未来を受け止めるのよ！
There's no way I can be forgiven
for the blood on my hands.
血に染まったこの手は
許されるはずもないだろう。
Still...
それでも　受け止めて。
Take hold of it!
うお～っ！
I won't rely on Izanagi anymore.
もう　イザナギには頼らない。
I'll accept reality
and move forward...
(現実を受け止め　前に進む))
Once one accepts the original outcome
and stops trying to run from it,
IZANAMI ACTIVATED
（イタチ）本来の
結果を受け入れ→
逃げなくなったとき
おのずと→
the loop will stop.
REALITY
イザナミのループは解ける。
This jutsu guides you toward
accepting your fate,
術に頼ることなく→
運命を自分で
受け入れるように導く術。
instead of relying on jutsu
to change it.
But a jutsu that has an escape
is too dangerous to use in actual combat.
抜け道のある術など
実戦では　危なくて使えない。
そういう意味で
イザナミは　禁術になっている。
That's why Izanami is
a Forbidden Jutsu.
If Kabuto stops trying
to transform himself,
だからカブトが　自分以外の誰かに
成り代わることをやめれば→
he can stop the loop.
ループから　出ることはできる。
うちは一族　闘争の歴史。
The strife-filled history
of the Uchiha...
The arrogance and recklessness
of those who used Izanagi...
その歴史の中で
イザナギに伴う術者のおごり。
個の暴走…。
そして　一族内での対立。
and how they clashed and
were stopped by Izanami...
それを止めるためのイザナミ。
I understand now
イザナギとイザナミが対の禁術として
存在する歴史はわかった。
why both Izanagi and Izanami
came to be Forbidden Jutsu.
And I see how one must learn
from the past
過去を教訓として
運命を受け入れ→
and accept one's fate
and move on.
前に進んでいくための戒め
というのも　わからなくはない。
But...
だが　なぜ…　なぜ　そんな術を
わざわざカブトにかけたんだ？
But why bother casting this
on Kabuto?
If there's a way to escape...
脱出できるってことは…。
He reminds me of the old me.
こいつは　昔の俺に似ていた。
He thinks by acquiring all there is,
すべてを手に入れたつもりで→
he can accomplish
whatever he wants.
何でもなせると猛進しようとする。
He makes himself
believe that he can't fail,
だからこそ　己の失敗におびえ→
己に失敗はないのだと
自分に　ウソをつく。
and lies to himself.
結果　それを
ごまかす方法として→
I stopped listening to anyone else.
I stopped trusting anyone.
他人の力を
信用しなくなったのが俺だ。
In Kabuto's case,
he is so deluded
カブトの場合は
それをごまかす方法として→
that he thinks all these powers
are his and his alone.
他人の力をもすべて
自分の力だと思い込んだ。
I empathize with him.
こいつのこともわかるんだ。
We were both used by
the shinobi world...
この忍の世に翻弄された者同士→
He can neither forgive himself
nor accept himself for what he truly is.
どうしても自分自身を許し
認めることができないことも…。
What he is doing is certainly wrong.
確かに　こいつの
やっていることは間違っている。
But he's not completely to blame
for not being able to realize that.
だが　こいつだけを
責めるのも間違いだ。
My chance has passed,
カブトには　俺と違い
死ぬ前に気づいてほしい。
but he can still forgive himself
before he dies.
Why would you ever feel
like you need to help him do that?
こんなやつのために→
なんで　兄さんが
そこまでする義理がある！？
He is not like you.
You were perfect!
こいつと兄さんは違う！
兄さんは完璧だった。
（イタチ）サスケ。
Sasuke...
I tried to control you
with the Visual Jutsu
俺は　別天神という
瞳術まで使い→
called Koto Amatsukami.
お前を操るかたちで
導こうとした。
I treated you like a child
誰よりも　お前を子供扱いし→
because I thought you
needed my protection.
守るべき対象としてしか見ず→
I didn't trust your strength.
お前の力を信用していなかった。
なんであれ　一つとして
一つで完璧なんてものは→
It may be that
a perfect being does not
exist at all in the world.
ないのかもしれない。
Sometimes two who seem
to be opposites
だからこそ　補うものが
引き寄せられるように生まれ→
are actually two sides
of the same coin.
They can only succeed when
they actually work together.
そばで対を成して→
初めて少しでも
よい方向へ近づけるのだと思う。
Like the Izanagi and Izanami.
イザナギとイザナミの術のように。
Look at me,
俺を見て　俺になかったものを
お前には探してほしい。
and find in yourself what
I was unable to find in myself.
Do not say I was perfect.
だから　俺を完璧だったなんて
言ってくれるな。
First of all...
まずは…。
Impossible!
（カブト）そんなはずはない！
僕は完璧になる存在だ！
I will be a perfect being!
This is... not me!
こんなのは…　僕じゃない！
How long will you
imitate Orochimaru?
いつまで
大蛇丸に成り代わっている！
If you want to exit this loop,
reexamine your mistakes!
このループから抜けたいなら
お前の失敗を見つめ直せ。
Shut up!
うるさい！
I know he's going to come at me
with a Fire Style Jutsu.
《ここで火遁がくるのは
わかっている》
Water Style...
Water Dragon...
水遁　水龍…。
水遁　水龍弾の術！
Water Style...
Water Dragon Missile!
うわっ！
He anticipated that jutsu
with Sharingan!
《写輪眼で　術の先読みを…》
How did I get this wrong?
何が失敗だったというんだ！？
Where did I...
make a mistake?
この僕のやってきた
どこに失敗があったと！？
（カブト）僕は　ただ
自分の存在を誰かに→
All I ever wanted was someone...
to appreciate...
who I was!
見てもらいたいだけだった！
All I wanted was to
be acknowledged!
認めてもらいたいだけだった！
Where is the mistake in that?!
それのどこが
失敗だったというんだ！
First of all...
まずは　ありのままの自分を→
you had to accept yourself
as you were.
自分自身が
認めてやることだった。
Then you wouldn't have
had to lie to anyone.
そうしえさえすれば
誰にもウソをつくことはなかった。
To you... or to me.
お前にも　俺自身にも。
If you lie to yourself,
how can you have friends?
ウソに信頼はなく
背中を預ける仲間はできん。
How can you trust or
be trustworthy?
そして…　ウソは
本当の自分すら見えなくさせる。
Lies will keep you from
ever seeing your true self.
《こんな…　こんなとこに
閉じ込められなきゃ→
If I wasn't trapped here...
I'd have won this war by now.
今頃　戦争に勝って…》
I'd be sleeping by now.
とっくに寝てる時間だったのに。
Damn you, Itachi!
イタチめ～！！
It's 9 o'clock already?
（ウルシ）もう９時か…。
Something wrong?
どうした？
いや→
No...
さっさと　この戦争を終わらせて
ゆっくり寝たいと思ってな。
I just wish we could
wrap this up quickly
so I could get a good night's sleep.
They never tell us lackeys
what's going on.
俺たち　末端の忍には
もう何が何やら。
詳しいことは
いつも　わかんねえしよ。
That's true.
まあな。
So, what are you gonna do
when this war is over?
お前　この戦争が終わったら
どうすんだ？
Well, I'll start by going home.
とりあえず　家に帰るかな。
If the war ends and
戦争が終わって　五大国が
このまま仲間でいるなら→
the Five Great Nations
continue to be allies...
then maybe my little brother who's been
on a mission for a long time,
ずっと任務で会えてない　弟も→
can finally come home.
帰ってきてるかも
しれないからさ。
帰る所があるやつは
うらやましいな。
I envy those who have
a home to return to...
You want to come with me?
お前も来るか？　俺と一緒に。
え？
Huh?
My home is an orphanage.
俺の家は　孤児院だからよ。
And if my kid brother's back,
he can take a look at your wounds.
それに　弟がいたら
傷をみてもらうといい。
ありがとう　ウルシ。
I appreciate that, Urushi!
《今度こそ
帰ってくるといいな…。
I really hope
you come back this time...
カブト》
Kabuto.
I'll stop the Reanimation Jutsu now.
これより　穢土転生の術を止める。
And... all the reanimated dead
will fade away.
（イタチ）これで…
転生の死人は　すべて消える。
That should end the war.
戦争も終わりの時が近づく。
But...
なら…　兄さん　あんたも…。
you'll be gone too, Brother.
I'll have protected my village as
俺は
木ノ葉隠れの　うちはイタチとして→
Itachi Uchiha of the Leaf
once again.
もう一度
忍里を守ることができる。
もう　この世界に未練はない。
I have no more regrets.
Why?!
なぜだ！　兄さんに→
Why help the very village that
put you where you are now?
あんなことをさせた
木ノ葉のために→
なんで　また兄さんが！？
You may be able to forgive,
but I cannot!
兄さんが許せても
俺が　木ノ葉を許せない！
You have no more regrets?
この世に未練がないだと？
What about what
you've made me become?!
俺を　こんなふうにさせたのは
兄さんなんだぞ！
ハァ　ハァ　ハァ…。
I leave Sasuke to you.
((サスケは　お前に任せる。
I tried to do everything myself...
and I failed.
俺は１人で何でもしようとし
失敗した。
This time... I will leave it
to my comrades.
(今度は
それこそ仲間に任せるさ))
I'm not the one who can
change you, Sasuke.
お前を変えられるのは
もう俺じゃない。
But I can stop this jutsu.
だから　せめて…
この術を止めることが→
今の俺にできること。
That will fulfill my promise
to Naruto, at least.
ナルトに託したことを
ないがしろにしないためにもな。
I will stop the Reanimation Jutsu!
（イタチ）穢土転生の術を止める。
印を教えろ。
Tell me the signs!
Tsukuyomi!
月読！
（イタチ）約束は果たした。
I kept my promise.
I leave the rest to you... Naruto.
あとは頼んだぞ。　ナルト。
gozen reiji akari kieta machi
At midnight, in a city where the lights are out
koyoi wa odore tipsy night
I'm going to dance tonight Tipsy Night
tsukiakari mo todokanu basho ni wa
In a place where the moonlight doesn't reach
kodoku sae mo utau machi ga aru
There's a city that brings loneliness
kuruisou na furuesou na itami dake ga
There's only a maddening pain that makes me tremble
kowaresou na nakushisou na houseki da
It's like a fragile gemstone that could be easily lost
kuraberareru koto nado ubawareru koto nado nai
There's nothing to compare it to and it can't be stolen
kimi wa kimi de ii, saa waratte misete
You should just be yourself, Now show me a smile
nani mo kangaezutomo soko ni riyuu ga nakutomo
Even you don't think, Even if there is no reason
sore koso ga subarashii hajimari
This is a wonderful beginning
saa, yoake da
Now, dawn is about to break
gozen reiji akari kieta machi
At midnight, in a city where the lights are out
furikaereba sasou black night town
I look back and it beckons me Black Night Town
I hate the Leaf Village for causing
you so much pain!
I hate it more than ever!
It's because I'm your brother that,
no matter what you say,
you're not going to stop me!
Even if you protect the village now,
I will still destroy it some day.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"I Will Love You Always"
Good bye... Big Brother.